are you liable suffering yeah
things can happen
on account of which
now I'd be pleased
so is that a problem
well I mean I'm just saying I still make
a problem out of these bad things yeah
no I mean suffering is a problem baby
you're liable to suffering is the
problem is it yeah
yeah
how do you know that
there is nothing now it's happening if
displeasing me in the present moment
yeah it's funny so how do I know that my
ability to suffering is a problem I
guess the thought of the possibility of
suffering but how do you know it's a
problem or otherwise yeah
so this say the thought of the
possibility of suffering mm-hmm just
enforceability of so you have the
possibility of stuff right now and
that's automatically assumed to be a
problem yes yeah and why it's a right
assumption by the way there's a problem
but how do you know how do you know that
how do you know it's problem what is the
measure cry like fair what is the
necessary base for craving feeling so
what is how is it felt unpleasant so
that's why it's a problem yeah cuz you
already suffer yeah and the fact that
you don't suffer right now yeah but you
could suffer so possibility of suffering
is suffering yeah and the reason why
when the directions because it can sound
as if oh well things can change and then
I'll suffer oh yeah yeah which means I
have to wait for things to change or try
to prevent them from changing in order
to be dealing with the suffering yeah I
mean even some people are from I had
people saying oh we all know what and
that's the point so you're not suffering
now doesn't mean you're free from
suffering no and or you suffering now
again doesn't mean you around the
suffering so to speak you run the
suffering when basically on the level of
possibility of suffering you don't know
the escape from the outside yeah that's
what it is it's not knowing this guy so
the actually enduring suffering if there
is presence of present here is impairing
that's unpleasant or absence of
presently enduring suffering doesn't
matter suffering is there because you're
still liable to the possibility of
suffering yeah and that is present can I
say it's not like
it's not being confident of being able
to
it's like maybe I'm wrong here like I
don't feel like I'm I've got no idea
about the escape from suffering but it's
not confidence like no matter what
this guy is no hmm well that's thing
yeah yeah so you don't know the escape
yeah because the escape is complete
well it's complete but it's also it's
not dependent on the type yes after any
escape of suffering in escape of nature
of something which means doesn't matter
what the content of that nature is yeah
in other words it's not like sometimes
you escape like this sometimes you
escape like that escape from suffering
is escape from that pliability to the
nature of suffering which means then it
doesn't matter what causes it you won't
need to deal with it because you don't
suffer on account with it so why do you
think then there is not enough
confidence in you
so think about in the level of feeling
that's kind of feeling yeah okay so it's
I guess that's one way of putting it
yeah it's like not liking unpleasant
feeling not having it again confidence
in being able to withstand any kind of
feeling about how unpleasant so the old
variety of feelings where can they be
come back and let me show ya where can
feelings be found
wait colorful is speaking where can you
feel those when oh right here right now
right now right so can you feel the
feeling in the closet can you feel the
feeling in the future no but it's easy
to assume that you can yes well it's
easy if if carelessness is a mode of
being thanks sure that needs to be dealt
as beforehand so naturally it doesn't
matter what past feeling you might
remember what future feeling you might
feel hopeful it's felt right now yeah
yeah so in as a container in itself
present enduring feeling can only be
felt now and it's inconceivable to make
it otherwise if you have to ignore it
have to actively engage with acts and
decisions and choices they will kind of
enable you to ignore the fact that it is
felt now it cannot not be felt now it's
impossible see you talked a lot recently about
see you talked a lot recently about
container
hmm miss the nature of containment
that's one of the characteristics of
containment that it's it's now yes of
course it can't not be the foundations
of mindfulness yeah it's not optional
that's what the one who understands that
is Allah says he stops thinking like oh
now I understood the nature of feelings
and the nature of anata in the past I
was now I'm not in the future but no no
that becomes what all that ceases to be
intelligible to think like that
oh I was before cuz it's not a linear
thing whatever it's felt right here
right now that's what has been
understood yeah that's what whatever has
the nature and arising he has been
understood I guess most people think of
in the past the future and stuff is like
is like yeah object it's an external
view upon yourself the cuher in this
objective factor of all that you can
observe independent of your point of
view of observation which is
inconceivable but back onto the
practical side of things more relevant
in this case now while we're speaking so
if you presently recognize that you are
liable to suffering the extent of your
liability to suffering cannot be
anywhere else except within that present
enduring feeling of suffering on account
of possibility to suffer
so anything that needs to be understood
cannot be anywhere else except in the
present exactly so you might take you
five days to understand it but it'll be
five days of understanding what's
present enduring not like in five days I
will arrive at something that's not here
now it is you know it's just cluttered
so you might take your number of days to
unclutter it while it is still here now
and the extent of that liability to
suffering whatever that is directly
corresponds to the extent that you
haven't understood present enduring feel
yeah but if you start thinking like this
you realize this what is it stopping you
then yeah I'm understanding it it's just
a simple attitude to this feeling yeah
attitude that there needs to be peeled
off there
so like it's allowing the currently
enduring feelings you just enjoy no
catch one I get involved in it yeah but
you can't completely you know deny that
in a sense of you can get overly
involved sure but you can also get
unduly yeah so to speak
in other words you do have a task of you
must understand it yeah so I can
understand it without / / leave old with
it yeah so you either way yeah he needs
to enjoy there you know stop denying it
you must stop acting out of it just like
the automated act towards craving as a
habit
and then you also can reevaluate on
account of present enduring feeling
whatever the feeling is you can
re-evaluate the extent of your liability
to suffering
am I still liable to what degree would
you say said that understanding they
said I cut the current feeling involves like
recognising that I was subjected to it
yeah sure that's part of it it's you
don't always have to go the same way
about it what you need to do is
recognize that there is something felt
yeah and then seeing what fundamental
category that will be sitting in
Pleasant Pleasant and then Oh that's
already you know being able to see that
what it means oh this is something
you're subjected to so you can say I
have this pleasant feeling this pleasant
feeling is mine and that's why I'm
acting protecting and trying to get more
of it but you have absolutely no say in
its pleasantness you cannot create
pleasantness of the pleasant feeling
you can only accept it yeah so what
makes pleasantness off of the pleasant
feeling it's inconceivable to you
it's just felt pleasantly yeah you can
try and rationalize afterwards as an
afterthought and so on but all of that
is in response to being subjected to the
pleasantness of a feeling and saying to
the unpleasantness of 18
and that's why you realize you cannot
possibly uproot that you can get under
it and like take the possession over
here so clarifying that type of image
context understanding discernment and
then also preventing the increasing of
the clutter of cover up through the
ranks rooted in greed aversion delusion
so sense restraint in and watchfulness
know what fun is for like who knows what
purpose I know you know exactly the
presidency presently induce a reason
feeling in jewels and if I'm not mindful
of its endurance on its own independent
of me I will be acting out of the
craving Travolta its automatic
yeah all you need to do is accept
ignorance ignoring it accept turning
your black blind eye to it except desire
for distraction and everything else will
follow effortlessly like floodgates all
these are these open it then all the
pressure just feel a lot
but within like within the mindfulness
of present endearing feeling you can do
whatever you want because you won't be
doing anything unwholesome because you
also think you need to be unmindful of
the present the nature the present Eric
field you can't do unwholesome things
mindfully and then the understanding can
only develop if whatever you're doing is
within yeah sure the official no no
completing it exactly then you'll be
coming with a familiar with the nature
of how feeling actually know how you
keep conceiving it to be that's the
thing it can't be you can see really
killing cuz it's because well that's
true for another yeah see you somebody
who is still considering the feeling
saying the feeling cannot truly be
conceived is true only in theory yeah
but that contradicts his actual state of
mind that does conceive it yeah so
that's we need to keep any mind because
that's how people fall into the view
that they think they understood yeah but
right view is or whatever chip is while
they know there's the petitioners that
is inconceivable it's either/or so yeah
you might have an idea about it and that
idea is true but it's far from being
having been applied to you I mean that's
like in assert that you probably have
that difference between acknowledge and
the direct knowledge but sometimes they
translate way
it starts by being just recollecting
what is the what what what feeling is
enduring right here right now and while
we're talking then once you recollect
that's more than enough as a container
as a base for mindfulness yeah
then when you think what do we do next
now well instead of following the
thought of what we do next you see the
need to do next within a container
exactly everything everything is a
feeling dispersed and now within this
feeling I have the State of Mind it's
doubtful and wondering what to do next
and you don't do anything because all
you need to do is stay rooted in the
container that you recollect of
presently enduring feeling that's how
eventually you learn how to stop acting
on feelings which requires loss of that
perspective of feeling so there is
unpleasant feeling in here I am basing
myself acting choosing to get rid of it
to understand it to rationalize it will
deal with it to manage it but if you're
properly mindful management becomes
impossible because any inclination
towards management is included within
present enduring feeling and that's
effortless you know managing anything
you're actually subduing your dependence
craving the need to manage these things
so doing it by including but you can't
include it as a mentor of your choice
you can't decide this is also included
that's not including Torah you need to
discern recollect that I had present
enduring feeling and then whatever is
simultaneous today that's why it's
included not because you made it so
because that's inevitably gonna happen
until the mind develops certain subtlety
in regard to this you'll be get the hint
of it and then you go around including
things you've been colluding and that's
not including which is right what you're
talking about is also about
understanding feeling something but
there's a thing you don't need to stop
including your things you just need to
include education you will include an
attitude not as a matter of choice
but as a matter of discernment
recollecting the right context the right
order whatever I'm trying to include
whatever I'm trying to manage whether
I'm trying to deal with things they
bother me things that pull me it doesn't
matter it's within the present enduring
healing and whatever I were to do
whatever I used to do it's within the
president during feeling that order
cannot be otherwise when the drugged
water becomes imperturbable yeah yeah
that's basically a small and there is
already a great deal of wisdom that you
cannot have that without understanding
what's going on yeah
you just cannot so like I had this
experience and I need to understand what
happened to me yeah me too I do know
you're just gonna be interpreted usually
in the terms that will be pleasing you
yes or playing into the views that you
hope you have
no this is about this it's that
somebody's based so against the context
present enduring feeling mm-hmm
did you recognize it's there a reason
you lieutenant you're subjected to it
you then also get to see the state of
your mind mind effective without my fee
from dad minded rage loss sensuality
mind it doesn't what's come to mind it I
know I'm not annoyed against or we
didn't the container present Indian
feeling what what do I do next you see
that within the container to present
enduring feeling so they don't do
anything you see that we are the present
thing an enduring container of how long
they do this for question feeling comes
first yeah
so if you am wandering off so what what
can I do then well you cannot do
anything anymore but things will be done
yeah that's never going to do anything
yeah you doing it yeah you just you'll
just find things being done and by that
point it will be impossible for those
things to be anything other than
wholesome or neutral they cannot be a
wholesome because that requires you
choosing that because unwholesome
certified definition is converting the
order everything you order isn't and now
the order is imperturbable that's
whatever is done cannot be an awesome
that's why certain things so the banner
cannot do certain things other hand
cannot do like impossible to be done
because it requires a necessity of that
wrong order not seen first is first not
seeing present enduring feeling whatever
they're feeling is pleasant unpleasant
neither present around present is a
necessary container for any act rooted
in in you craving doesn't matter
and you realize you'll be then quite
content with whatever container there is
doesn't matter anymore even unpleasant
feeling so to speak will not be source
of unhappiness because happy and happier
content discontent it's only the state
of your mind within the container
exactly but it's basically state of your
mind that either it resists against the
container tries to like take possession
of it
in order to feed that whatever it is
bothering or during the mind so it's
trying to deal with it there is always a
pressure a burden a requirement that you
think dealing with it defending myself
against these feelings all that becomes
inconceivable coz whatever demand
presents it's seen within the right
order of present enduring feeling and
that's quite indifferent already yes at
all of that resisting is actually about
trying to involve trying to change the
order cuz you call then resisting I can
control yeah although resisting is
rooted into assuming that you can't
change yeah and that's like that's why that's
yeah and that's like that's why that's
basically definition concede is that
subtle version whereby district point of
view assumes to that extent itself to
becoming first
so then you'll be happy amidst pain not
like enjoying it sensually but you will
not be discontent even if there is
unpleasant feeling enduring for days
because this content is nothing what
feeling you subjected to this content is
in that pressure of it which is of
course hand in hand when you attempting
to deal with it manage it remove it
crave against it crave for it whatever
exercise basically effort towards it
rather than any F will you sing you
might then you understand you don't say
anything you said yes no to both neither
is within that and that's so even if
you're trying to go through warden to
grab it to do with it to remove it to
destroy it to repossess it it's always a
step ahead yeah because it's determined
by how far you step that's how far it
goes so you cannot possibly step outside
of it so if you want to be happy as in
free from suffering see what feeling is
there and doesn't matter if it's not
happiness yeah and then see that whatever attitude
yeah and then see that whatever attitude
you have towards it
yeah container is within that yeah not
other way around and stick to that and
you will be unable to suffer even if you
were to want to suffer mmm it becomes
English subjects suffering becomes
inconceivable yeah
very clear instructions which needs to
be done Oh